Joseph Dela Rutledge papers M2235
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Joseph Dela Rutledge papers
1951-1958
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Rutledge, Joseph D., 1928-2016
M2235
0.25 Linear Feet (1 half manuscript box, 1 map folder)
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Dela Rutledge (1928-2016) worked at the Eckert-Mauchly Computer Corporation which later became the UNIVAC division of Remington Rand. While at Reminton Rand, Rutledge was one of the engineers responsible for the development of UNIVAC. He went on to work at IBM from 1958-2003.
Scope and Contents
Materials consist of 66 documents of Joseph Dela Rutledge's papers related largely to his work at the Eckhert-Mauchly Computer Corporation and Remington Rand Corporation. Includes printed ephemera (much of it related to UNIVAC), conference papers, discount cards, correspondence, newspaper clippings, notes, blueprints, invoices, a travel expense voucher, and more. The papers show his involvement with the design and engineering of the UNIVAC computer.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford Libraries in; 2017. Accession MSS 2017-166.
Univac computer -- History; Computer industry -- United States -- History; Rutledge, Joseph D., 1928-2016; Remington Rand, Inc.
- Matrix Algebra Programs for the UNIVAC by Joseph Rutledge and Harvey Rubinstein. Copy of typed paper presented at the Wayne Conference on Automatic Computing Machinery and Applications, Detroit, Michigan, 1951-03-27-1951-03-28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- High Order Matrix Computation on the UNIVAC by Joseph Rutledge and Harvey Rubinstein. Copy of typed paper presented at the Pittsburgh meeting of the Association for Computing Machinery, 1952-05-03 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- An Application of Large Scale Computation to Economics by Emil D. Schell. Typescript paper presented at the Association for Computing Machinery, Pittsburgh, PA, 1952-05-02-1952-05-03 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Manuscript outline and mathematical notations, unsigned but presumed to be Rutledge's handwriting, 7pp (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Text with pencil tics on some letters as if creating an alpha code for machine reading letter, and pencil drawings on verso; 2pp (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Flowchart of the history of computing from Babbage and including Radar, Hollerith-IBM, Bell Relay and others; mimeograph, 1953-12-04 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper clippings and cartoon about UNIVAC (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Printed cards including UNIVAC system, identification card, discount cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Summary of census UNIVAC log, specific dates in 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remington Rand, Inc. Pulse Code, 1951-11-26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Booklets: Remington Rand Employees Insurance Plan and Employees' Accident and Sickness Benefit Plan, 1956-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bill, check receipt for consulting services for Remington Rand, Sperry Rand (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Traveling expense vouchers incurred for UNIVAC and UARC, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hotel rates in Washington, D. C.; Logistics Research Project, memo: We are not sending you a copy of the final program...", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Telecomputing Corporation, Specification for Telereader Type 29A, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Operating Instructions Output Edit 240-9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brief Description of MINAC (alias Frankel machine), 2pp, typescript (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Coded computer print-out, 1 pp (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pencil data in columnar format (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Underwood Corp, N. Y., trade brochure: ELECOM 2: low cost Electronic Computers (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Joseph Rutledge while at Remington Rand Univac, including with Anatol Holt, and with Arnold Rose, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from Joseph Rutledge to Dr. Mauchly informing him of accepting IBM's offer, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from Anatol W. Holt to Dr. Richard Stark, Mathematical Analysis Unit, Knolls Atomic Power Laboratory, relating to the crystal structure problem which was run on the UNIVAC, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Re names in compiling systems - a classification which might possibly be complete, 1p; On the assignment of AB registers in LARC, 2pp, both by by J. D. Rutledge, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- On the subject of tags: proposal; General nomenclature system for G. P. II (Box 1, Folder 6)
- UNIVAC Applications Research Center, UNIVAC IIR Specifications, mimeograph, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Proposed Advanced Coding System for UNIVAC-LARC by Frances E. Holberton, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Matrix Math Flow Charts, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Problem / LMO Edit Compiler, 1p (Box 1, Folder 7)
- There Once Was a System, short story, 6pp, typed (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Westinghouse Electrical Company, invoices (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Report: Standard Coding Procedures for Car-programmed Electronic Calculator Floating Decimal Board no. 1, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Application of the Kodak Minicard System to Problems of Documentation, presented at the Annual Meeting, American Documentation Institute, Cleveland, Ohio, November 4-5, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- IBM Electronic Punched Card Accounting Machines; Principles of Operation. Electronic Calculating Punch Type 606 and Accounting Machine Types 402 and 403 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Arithmetic Unit-PBC 2-5 cycle blue-print. Eckert-Mauchly Computer Corp., Philadelphia, PA. (Map-folder 2)
- Plug board layout blue-print. Eckert-Mauchly Computer Corp, Philadelphia, PA (Map-folder 2)
- RemRand News, vol VI, no. 8, NY, 1955-04 (Map-folder 2)